<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mircea Lungu</title>
    <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/tags/ecosystems/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Mircea Lungu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Mircea F Lungu</copyright>
    <atom:link href="/tags/ecosystems/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper: Bootstrapping an Ubiquitous Ecosystem @ WEA&#39;16</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-09-20-bootstrapping-an-ubiquitous-ecosystem/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-09-20-bootstrapping-an-ubiquitous-ecosystem/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;An unconventional idea for an ecosystem, which shows well that there are many more opportunities to benefit from the ecosystem idea, than the various industrial applications. The concrete examples of the platform and the applications make the ideas tangible and well understandable. I particularly like the discussions of the lessons learned [&amp;hellip;]&amp;rdquo; (a reviewer for the paper :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved that review!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was happy to hear that my paper on Bootstrapping a Ubiquitous Monitoring Ecosystem (&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/mircealungu/Bootstrapping_an_Ecosystem__WEA16/blob/master/preprint.pdf&#34;&gt;preprint online&lt;/a&gt;) was accepted for presentation at WEA (Workshop on Ecosystem Architectures) that will take place in Copenhagen and is colocated with ECSA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The paper talks about some of the challenges and
opportunities that come with bootstrapping a
ubiquitous monitoring ecosystem. It is a case
study inspired from our &lt;a href=&#34;https://zeeguu.unibe.ch&#34;&gt;Zeeguu&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Stack Overflow @ SSE&#39;13</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/13-09-01-visualizing-stack-overflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/13-09-01-visualizing-stack-overflow/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://mircealungu.github.io/img/stackoverflow.png&#34; alt=&#34;visualizing-stack-overflow&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;&amp;ldquo;A nobel prize is waiting for the one who visualizes the economy
of information&amp;rdquo;&lt;/b&gt; (Steward Brand, Inventing the Future at MIT)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my current travelling companions is “The Media Lab – Inventing the Future at MIT” by Steward Brand. Like several other books about the history of computing in the 80s, this one is also fascinating and it shows again how much ahead of their time were people in those years… and how we are still reaping the ideas that they saw. The book reports on an anecdote by Harlan Cleveland :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“I have wanted for some time to find a map of information flows around the world. The other day I had one hour to kill between appointments in new york city, so I dropped into the Rand-McNally shop to ask for such a map. My request created quite a stir, and virtually every employee was called into consultation. They brought out all sorts of maps showing flows of food and feedgrains, oil and coal, weapons and manufacturers – but finally admitted that they had no map of information flows and didn’t think their competitors had one either.” (Steward Brand, Inventing the Future at MIT, pp. 245)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-software-engineering-information-flow&#34;&gt;The Software Engineering Information Flow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can we make maps of information flow in the world today? In the article about StackOverflow that we will present at SSE in Saint Petersburg this summer we show that we can at least map components of this information transfer; in our particular case software engineering knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The StackOverflow database, of which dumps are publicly available, contains information about how knowledge is transferred between users in the form of questions and answers. Since a large number of users have provided their geolocation information in their profiles we can build a hierarchical graph of this data and visualize it with Quicksilver. We grabbed a public dump of the SO data curated by Alberto Bacchellii and Luca Ponzanelli at the University of Lugano.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this data we created the map of the flow of knowledge in the world through StackOverflow as a medium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://mircealungu.github.io/img/stackoverflow-full.png&#34; alt=&#34;stackoverflow-full&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map is built using the following conventions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Countries and continents are represented using treemaps. Their areas are proportional to the aggregated reputation received by their corresponding users (e.g. UK has 10x more reputation than Switzerland)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The arrows indicate the flow of information between continents. The thickness of an arrow is proportional to the number of answers (e.g. Australia imports three times more information than it exports)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several observations on this map:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;America and Europe are the main contributors&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Small countries like Switzerland or Sweden have disproportionately high reputation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;China is almost invisible even if Joel &lt;a href=&#34;https://stackoverflow.blog/2011/04/stack-overflow-around-the-world/&#34;&gt;reports&lt;/a&gt; a large number of visits from China.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Africa does not contribute much&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The map is taken from our paper (&lt;a href=&#34;http://scg.unibe.ch/archive/papers/Sche13a-GeolocatingStackOverflow.pdf&#34;&gt;pdf&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://scg.unibe.ch/scgbib?_k=dvvBNH0e&amp;amp;query=Sche13a&amp;amp;display=bibtex&#34;&gt;Bibtex&lt;/a&gt;) which contains more details about the data collection and analysis (including details on geo-locating users, and the evolution over time of the data).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you read it we would love to get your feedback in the comments section of this blog entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime think about the following questions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could the SO Knowledge Flow map be representative of the way computing knowledge is distributed in the world? What does it say about our world?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Could the fact that SO is in English be the main reason for US and UK to be so much ahead of the other countries in terms of reputation?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
