<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Research on Mircea Lungu</title>
    <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/tags/research/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Research on Mircea Lungu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Mircea F Lungu</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 12:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/research/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>PhD Scholarship in Software Engineering</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/17-05-31--phd-scholarhsip/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/17-05-31--phd-scholarhsip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Within the context of the University PhD Scholarships Programme, applications are invited for an opening in the Software Engineering and Architecture Research Group at the University of Groningen in the Netherlands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Scholarship Programme, selected prospective PhD students are invited to write their own PhD research proposal in collaboration with an expert PhD supervisor from the University of Groningen with whom they want to work. As a PhD scholarship student you have the opportunity to let your curiosity drive your research at the boundaries of knowledge. More details about the programme are available online [1]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Software Engineering and Architecture Research Group carries research in software engineering with a focus on architecture, evolution analysis, and intelligent tools for software development. We are interested in particular in candidates who have a strong background and interest in one of the following research directions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;software analysis&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;software visualization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;program understanding&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;software ecosystem evolution&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;accelerating knowledge acquisition&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;run-time monitoring of software systems&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The University of Groningen, one of the oldest universities in the Netherlands, is home to a vibrant international student body. The university constantly ranks in the top 100 universities in the world. The city of Groningen has an active cultural scene and the university sports center offers a wide range of athletic activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To apply, please send an email, including a short statement of research interest and CV with at least two references to Dr. Mircea Lungu m.f.lungu@rug.nl by June 30, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rug.nl/education/phd-programmes/phd-scholarship-programme/&#34;&gt;http://www.rug.nl/education/phd-programmes/phd-scholarship-programme/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
