<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Mircea Lungu</title>
    <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Mircea Lungu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2016 Mircea F Lungu</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 10:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mircealungu.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using a Performance Monitor to Illustrate the Power of DB Indexes</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/18-09-07--db-indexes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2018 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/18-09-07--db-indexes/</guid>
      <description>TL;DR;
- Database indexes are easy and powerful tools for performance enginering - An internal performance monitor enables quick insights into service performance  &amp;nbsp;
Prologue: Two Research Projects Project #1 - In Zeeguu we research how we can make learning a foreign language more fun. We monitor a learners interactions with foreign texts and based on this we recommend further personalized reading and personalized vocabulary exercises.
The Zeeguu web application has a classical client-server architecture with the backend being implemnted with Flask &amp;ndash; one of the most popular web application frameworks for Python.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Starting as Associate at IT University in Copenhagen</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/18-07-01--started-at-itu/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/18-07-01--started-at-itu/</guid>
      <description>I am glad to announce that I have started as Associate Professor at the IT University in Copenhagen. I will be teaching Software Architecture, Technical Interaction Desgin, and Advanced Software Engineering. I will also be continuing my work on software evolution, software ecosystems, and using technology to enhance personalized learning. The building looks amazing. The colleagues are diverse and telented. And the city is as bike-friendly as Groningen was. I have a feeling that is &amp;ldquo;the beginning of a beautiful friendship&amp;rdquo; :)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invited Talk at the SEN Symposium</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/17-01-20--sen-symposium-talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/17-01-20--sen-symposium-talk/</guid>
      <description>The SEN symposium in Amsterdam is a yearly event that gathers software engineering researchers and practitioners. This year I was invited to give a talk along several great speakers including: Felienne Hermans, Andreas Zeller, Marielle Stoelinga, and Hans Wanders the CIO (!) of the Netherlands.

I started my talk observing that Google, Facebook, and Twitter are using context in order to provide us with the best&amp;hellip; ads! I then argued that in software analytics we can use context in order to create more powerful tools and analyses.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📝 Analysis Bots</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/17-01-19-analysis-bots/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 Jan 2017 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/17-01-19-analysis-bots/</guid>
      <description>The Story Our paper on analysis bots has been accepted to the ICSE ERA track. The paper is co-written with Ivan Bestchastnick from University of British Columbia and Yanyan Zhuang from the University of Colorado.
The paper is written from the perspective of software engineering researchers and for a software engineering audience. It argues that we must implement a platform where analysis bots compete to provide the most meaningful analysis results to practitioners.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>🎉 Nominated for the Teacher of the Year Award</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-11-20-teacher-of-the-year/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2016 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-11-20-teacher-of-the-year/</guid>
      <description>I have been nominated for the teacher of the year award! Especially after seeing all the other nominations I started feeling like I don&amp;rsquo;t deserve the honor. However, it is also true that together with my team, we put a lot of effort in coming up with cool project ideas and running them in the timespan of five months.
Thus, many thanks and congratulations for my teaching assistants: Laura Baakman, Jeroen Brandsma, Georgios Digkas, Sybren Gjaltema, Jelle van Wezel, Angelo Karountzos, Alexander Lukjanenkovs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📝 Polite Programmers, Use Sentence Case</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-11-20-polite-smalltalk-at-nool/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2016 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-11-20-polite-smalltalk-at-nool/</guid>
      <description>The programming languages reseachers have a healthy sense of humor. The -1th edition of the NOOL (New Object Oriented Languages) Workshop had a very creative call for papers. To keep up with the state of affairs, Jan Kurs and I submitted a paper with a most concise abstract:
 JavaProgrammersUseCamelCaseToSeparateWordsInIdentifiers.  Pythonistas_and_others_use_underscore_in_their_identifiers.  Polite programmers can use spaces if they like.
 The paper presents briefly some of the design decisions that went into Polite, our evolutionary mutation of Smalltalk that brings the language closer to natural language.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Course: Introduction to Data Science</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-11-16-introduction-to-data-science-course/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-11-16-introduction-to-data-science-course/</guid>
      <description>Today, with Kerstin Bunte, we are starting our new course on Introduction to Data Science. This will be interesting: we have 60 first year master students from computer science, astronomy, and mathematics. What do they have in common? What topics can we cover such that most of them can benefit? Which topics are not too easy nor too challenging? We&amp;rsquo;ll see!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📝 Ubiquitous Monitoring Ecosystems</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-09-20-bootstrapping-an-ubiquitous-ecosystem/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2016 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/16-09-20-bootstrapping-an-ubiquitous-ecosystem/</guid>
      <description>The Story I wrote a paper for the Ecosystem Architectures event (WEA&amp;rsquo;16) about the design of an ecosystem of applications which monitor a learner&amp;rsquo;s interactions with knowledge.
 &amp;ldquo;An unconventional idea for an ecosystem, which shows well that there are many more opportunities to benefit from the ecosystem idea, than the various industrial applications. The concrete examples of the platform and the applications make the ideas tangible and well understandable.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📝 Evolutionary and Collaborative Software Architecture Recovery </title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/14-01-01-evolutionary-and-collaborative-software-architecture-recovery/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2014 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/14-01-01-evolutionary-and-collaborative-software-architecture-recovery/</guid>
      <description>Our work on Softwarenaut has finally been published in the Science of Computer Programming. The paper (pdf, bibtex,citations) introduces Softwarenaut, a visual, interactive architecture recovery tool which leverages evolutionary analysis to support source code understanding.
This page contains a very high level description of the tool. For details and case studies, see
 the journal article that describes the tool (preprint pdf, bibtex)
 the conference paper that describes the way we visualized hierarchical clusterings of software systems (preprint pdf, bibtex)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>📝 Mapping the Open Information Economy</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/13-09-01-visualizing-stack-overflow/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2013 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/13-09-01-visualizing-stack-overflow/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;A nobel prize is waiting for the one who visualizes the economy of information&amp;rdquo; (Steward Brand, The Media Lab)
One of my current travelling companions is “The Media Lab – Inventing the Future at MIT” by Steward Brand. Like several other books about the history of computing in the 80s, this one is also fascinating and it shows again how much ahead of their time were people in those years… and how we are still reaping the ideas that they saw.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Keynote at Smalltalks in Argentina</title>
      <link>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/12-11-11-keynote-smalltalks-argentina/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Nov 2012 12:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mircealungu.github.io/post/12-11-11-keynote-smalltalks-argentina/</guid>
      <description>I was invited to give a keynote at Smalltalks in Argentina. Before the conference I spent some time with students at the University of Buenos Aires with Gabriela Arevallo and the other organizers of the conference. The conference was great. The argentinian Smalltalk community is extremely welcoming and passionate. I look forward to going back one day.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>